Register of the Jacques de Launay Papers, 1914-1993
Hoover Institution Archives
Jacques de Launay Papers,
1914-1993
75013
Launay, Jacques de
13 manuscript boxes, 4 phonotape reels, 2 phonorecords. (5.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to various aspects of twentieth-century European history, and especially to Romania and Belgium during World War II; the Little Entente; the relationship between Adolf Hitler and Lord Rothermere, 1933-1939; the Walloon Legion during World War II; and education in Europe. Includes sound recordings of interviews by J. de Launay of Tadeusz Komorowski, Andre Francois-Poncet, Georges Bonnet, and Jules Moch.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945.; Rothermere, Harold Sidney Harmsworth, 1st viscount, 1868-1940.; Waffen-SS. Legion Wallonie.; Little Entente, 1920-1939.; Education.; Education--Europe.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Belgium.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Romania.; Belgium.; Europe.; Germany.; Germany--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Great Britain.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Germany.; Romania.; Romania--History.; Phonotapes.; Phonorecords.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1943, 1945-46
  - Colson, General, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Corap, General, 1943, 1945-46
  - Georges, General André, 1946
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1947
  - Avramovski, A., "An Attempt to Transform the `Petite Entente' Into a Pact of Mutual Assistance Against All Aggression" (in French) (Box 1)
  - Batowski, Henryk
    - "Central Europe in the Policy of Great Powers in the Period 1919-1939/41", Warsaw, 1970
    - "Joseph Beck's Voyage in Romania in October 1938" (in French), Polish Institute for International Affairs, Warsaw, 1960
  - Campus, Eliza
    - "The Position of the `Petite Entente' in Relation to the Austro-German Tariff Union Plan" (in French), reprint, Nouvelles Etudes D'Histoire (Bucharest), 1965
    - "The Fight to Achieve Romanian National Unity (1914-1918)" (in French), reprint, Revue Roumaine D'Histoire (Bucharest), Vol. IV, No. 4, 1965
    - "Nicolae Titulescu and the Politics for the Maintenance of Romanian Territorial Integrity" (in French), reprint, Revue Roumaine D'Histoire (Bucharest), Vol. V, No. 3, 1966
  - Deutsch, R.
    - "The Foreign Policy of Romania and the Dynamics of Peace, 1932-1936", reprint, Revue Roumaine D'Historie (Bucharest), Vol. 1, No. 1, 1966
    - "Romania and the Problem of the Straits at Montreux in 1936" (in French), reprint, Revue Roumaine D'Histoire (Bucharest), Vol, VI, No 1, 1967
  - Goy, R., de, "The Walloon Legion, 1941-1945" (in French)
  - Matthys, Victor, an appeal (in French) before the Charleroi War Council, July 4, 1946
  - Radesco, General Nicolae, report (in French) on the events of October 13 and December 7 at Bucharest, August 26, 1947
  - Verschaeve, Cyriel, last appeal (in German), undated
  - Walloon Legion (Legion Wallonie), 1941-44, clippings
  - WRITINGS, 1959, 1975
    - "The Future and Professional Education of Youth in Europe" (in French), Brussels, 1959
    - "Secret Stories of Belgium, 1935-1945" (in French), Part III, with annotations by Leon Degrelle, Paris, 1975
- INCREMENT, 1975
  - SUBJECT FILE
    - Launay, Jacques de: "La Correspondence secrete Hitler-Rothermere," 1933-1939. (Unpublished study of the most important correspondence between Lord Rothermere, editor of the Daily Mail, London, and Adolf Hitler, mainly concerning German-English and German-French relations in the 1930's, etc. (Box 1)
- INCREMENT, 1978
  - SUBJECT FILE
    - Besse, Fernand (Box 2)
      - "Position des travailleurs Chretiens en matiere d'Apprentissage" (in French), mimeographed, Journees europeennes d'information sur la formation professionnelle de jeunes, n.p., n.d.
    - Bureau European de la Jeunesse
      - "Extraits de presse obtenus et en Belgique a partir du 15 Mai 1962" (in French), newspaper clippings, La Lanterne, and other newspapers, 1962
    - Bureau European de la Jeunesse et de l'enfance
      - Documents (in French), published, (Bruxelles), 1952-1956. Printed copies.
    - Chaudieu, Georges
      - "Une experience de formation humaine dans une ecole professionnelle" (in French), Journees Europeennes sur la formation professionnelle des jeunnes (Geneve), Juillet 1950. Printed copy.
    - Commission Europeenne de la Formation Professionnelle de Jeunes
      - "Dans une ecole neuve un nouveau programme d'enseignement general" (in French), n.p., n.d. Printed copy.
      - "La formation professionnelle des jeunes filles dans les metiers industriels" (in French), n.p., n.d. Printed copy.
      - Sepe, Giovanni. "La formation professionnelle des jeunes dans l'artisanat en Italie" (in French), (Roma), n.d. Printed copy.
    - Coseil National du Patronat Francais. Commission d'Apprentissage.
      - "Organisation professionnelle de l'Apprentissage - enquete 1949" (in French), n.p., n.d. Printed copy.
    - L'Europe, Congres de
      - "Provisional programme; "Rapport politique" (in English and French), The Hague, 1948. Printed copy.
    - Falkenhausen, General von - Interrogations, 1946 (in French), photoreproduction of 9 typewritten pages translation of the original German text, May 28, 1946. Photocopy (positive typescript)
    - "Le Federalisme" (in French), La Federation, Paris, n.d. Printed copy.
    - "Les forces armees de la Federation Europeenne" (in French), n.p., n.d. Printed copy.
    - Guebriant, M. de
      - "La formation professionnelle agricole" (in French), Supplement, Chambres d'Agriculture, Septembre-Octobre 1952 (Fontaineblau). Printed copy.
    - Hitler, Adolf
      - Babtisme de Feu de Adolf Hitler (in German), correspondence (in English and German) related to the battles in August 1914, in which Hitler participated as a volunteer. The correspondence took place between Col. Earl, British Armed Forces and Dr. Otto Schwend, German Officer, photostat copies except for one original letter. Includes 5 photographs, 1914-1970
      - Adolf Hitler's letter to Joseph Popp (in German), photograph, with a typewritten French translation, 1914.
      - "Localisation des aquarelles de Hitler" (in French), 6 photographs and 2 xerox copies of Hitler's paintings; 12 photographs of people, houses, scenes. A newspaper clipping (in French), showing and with information relative to one of Hitler's paintings "Houbourdin," January 16, 1976
    - International Labour Conference, Conference internationale du Travail, "Recommendation 87," 32d session, July 1, 1949 (in English and French), n.p., n.d. Printed copy.
    - Launay, Jacques de, and Bourgeois, Henri. "L'utilisation des gaz asphyxiants 1914-1918" (in French), a typewritten list.
    - Lousse, Emile. A resume (in French), n.d. Typewritten copy.
    - Mouvement Francais pour les Etats-Unis d'Europe. "Note d'information" (in French), Lille, n.d. Printed copy.
    - "L'Orientation professionnelle en France" (in French), La Documentation Francaise. Notes et etudes documentaires. (Paris), 12 Septembre 1950
    - Principaux traits caracteristiques de l'apprentissage en Italie" (in French), Fournees Europeennes d'Information sur la Formation Professionnelle des Jeunnes, Avril 1950.
    - Union Europeenne des Federalistes, 2e annuel Congres de, (in French), Rome, 6-11 Novembre 1948, printed & mimeographed, programs, motions, resolutions, 1948.
    - Venlo, L'Incident de, (in French), photostat, n.p., n.d. Photocopy (typescript).
Sound Recording Tapes
- BOR-KOMOROVSKI, General - "L'Insurrection de Varsovie", Enregistrement réalisé à Londres par J. de Launay, 13 Decembre 1960. (Reel A)
- FRANÇOIS-PONCET, A. - "Ma Mission Auprès du Duce (1938-39)", Enregistrement réalisé chez M. François-Poncet, Paris, 1 Mars 1958. (Reel B)
- BONNET, Georges - "La Periode 1933-39 - Souvenirs", Enregistrement réalisé à Bergneustadt (RFA) par J. de Launay, 26 Avril 1957. (Reel C)
- MOCH, Jules - "La Naissance du Front Populaire 1936", Enregistrement réalisé à Lausanne par J. de Launay, 1 avril 1959. (Reel D)